Mss.Ms.Coll.200
American Philosophical Society
Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, 1668-1983
Bulk, 1750-1850
Mss.Ms.Coll.200
American Philosophical Society
25.0 Linear feet
Though the Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection is composed of items that do not fall readily into any other existing collection, the two dominant intellectual areas represented in the collection are Early American History and History of Science.
25 linear feet.
Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
Banks, Joseph, Sir, 1743-1820
Cooper, Thomas, 1759-1839
Coues, Elliott, 1842-1899
Cuvier, Georges, Baron, 1769-1832
Darlington, William, 1782-1863
Edison, Thomas A., (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931
Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
Everett, Edward, 1794-1865
Fitch, John
Genth, F. A., (Frederick Augustus), 1820-1893
Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872
Harding, Warren G.
Newcomb, Simon
Newton, Isaac, Sir, 1642-1727
Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851
Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796
Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864
Seybert, Adam,1773-1825.
Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866
Stevens, Henry
Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872
Thomson, Charles, 1729-1824
Various authors
Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
Wayne, Anthony
Box 1-49
Scope and Contents note
The Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection is composed of items that do not fall readily into other collections. The two dominant intellectual areas represented in the collection are early American history and the history of science.
In the collection there are letters by, and material relating to, James Madison, Benjamin Franklin, William and Thomas Penn, Horatio Gates, John Hancock, Pierre Eugene du Simitiere, William Pitt, the U. S. Continental Congress, Benedict Arnold, George Washington, General Lafayette, Albert Gallatin. Also of interest is James Logan’s “Questionnaire used basis of testimony in the Penn-Maryland boundary dispute,” and George III’s 1783 Commission to David Hartley to negotiate peace with the thirteen United States.
Additionally, the collection holds a variety of material about the French and Indian War, the American Revolution, and non-importation resolutions. There is also such items as a petition to John Adams from “sundry female inhabitants of Philadelphia” asking for the release of prisoners from Fries Rebellion (1799); Jared Sparks correspondence concerning the publication of the Franklin Letters; and a facsimile of Lee’s General Order No. 9, surrendering the Army of Northern Virginia (April 10, 1865).
In the history of science, the collection holds letters by, and material relating to, many of the big names in science, especially natural philosophers of the 18th century but including scientists through into the 1930s. Among those represented are Johannes Fredericus Gronovious, John Bartram, Horace-Bénédict de Saussure, Pierre Eugène Du Simitière, William Herschel, William Dunbar, James Rumsey and the Rumsian Society, Sir Joseph Banks, Jean Baptiste de Lamarck, James Edward Smith, Charles L. Bonaparte, Sir David Brewster, William Buckland, George Cuvier, Michael Faraday, Louis Agassiz, Edward Hitchcock, Benjamin Silliman, Charles Wilkes, Elisha Kent Kane, John Tyndall, Francis Trevelyan Buckland, Thomas Edison, Lord Kelvin, Nikola Tesla, Max Born and Max Planck.
Also included is material related to the Bristol Institution; a letter asking Lord Kelvin permission to use "Kelvin" as measurement for electricity (May 3, 1892); a letter signed by Albert Einstein, from Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists, asking for money to educate the public about the responsibility of atomic energy; Neils Bohr’s “Challenge to Civilization”; letters concerning the development of physics and atomic energy, answering questions from E. Chudzicki. Together this material highlights the emerging fields of geology, astronomy, physics, natural history, ornithology, botany, chemistry and genetics.
Native American Images note: Nearly 200 black and white silver gelatin photographs, negatives, slides, and photomechanical prints of Iroquois chiefs, signatures, scenes of the Isleta pueblo, Ojibwa portraits, Penobscot attire, and Baffinland Inuits. Copies of images from Catlin, Parsons, McKenney, Speck and Boas are found. Of note, pictographs of Iroquois signatures are represented by symbols of hatchets, deer, turtles, arrows, and pipes. Each name is identified with the date of the signing of various eighteenth century treaties. Referenced in Freeman’s Guide to manuscripts relating to the American Indian, number 1644.
Naval History Note
There are numerous items in this collection which may be of interest to students of naval history:
Barry, John, 1745-1803.
United States, Continental Congress. Letter to John Barry. 1776 April 11. Relative to prize sloop Edward. 1 page.
Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.
Byrd, Richard Evelyn. Letter to Mrs. Anna Lane Lingelbach. 1950 April 5. Appeal to help save people in Soviet concentration camps. 1 item.
Humphreys, Joshua, 1751-1838.
Humphreys, Joshua. Letterbook, with letters to Tench Francis, Thomas Truxton, etc. pertaining to ships for the navy. 1797 August - 1797 November. Correspondence. 7 pages.
Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792.
Jones, John Paul. Letter to General William Whipple. 1777 December 11. Reporting on trip of the Ranger, refers to U. S. commissioners. 3 pages.
Jones, John Paul. Letter to Robert Morris. 1779 October 13. News of his activities including the battle between the Bon Homme Richard and the Serapis on September 23, mentions Dr. Franklin. 4 pages.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to Naval School of Philadelphia. 1843 January 17. Thanking for information. 1 page.
Fitzroy, Robert. Letter to W. Hepworth Dixon. 1860 November 29. Will review Matthew Fontaine Maury's work. 4 pages.
Fitzroy, Robert. Letter to W. Hepworth Dixon. 1860 December 17. Concerning his review of Matthew Fontaine Maury. 3 pages.
Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860.
Paulding, James Kirke. Letter to John Vaughan. 1839 March 18. Enclosing new plan for keeping log book at sea, by Captain E. Beaufort of the British Admiralty. 1 page.
Poinset, Joel R. Letter to John Vaughan. 1839 June 28. Encloses note from James Kirke Paulding. Hopes to visit Philadelphia by the end of July. Mr. Sully in Washington. 2 pages.
United States. Navy.
Barton, William P. C. Letter to C. H. Stedman. 1842 January 1. Concerning J. Francis Tuckerman and his examination for the U.S. Navy. 2 pages.
Barton, William P. C. Letter to Jacob Bigelow. 1842 January 7. Concerning J. Francis Tuckerman and his examination for the U.S. Navy. 2 pages.
Barton, William P. C. Letter to J. Francis Tuckerman. 1842 January 7. Concerning his treatment by members of the board and how he [Barton] has answered them at the naval board. 3 pages.
Hamilton, Harry D. Concerning the ships named Franklin. 1948 July 3. Concerning the ships named Franklin. 5 pages.
United States Naval Observatory.
Abbe, Cleveland. Letter to H. F. Peters. 1890 January 7. Astronomy, and proposal to rotate superintendency of the U.S. Naval Observatory. 3 pages.
Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877. United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).
Poinsett, Joel Roberts. Letter to Mahlon Dickerson. 1837 January 7. Wishes William Davis appointed to serve on the United States Exploring Expedition. 2 pages.
Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Thomas Ap Catesby Jones. 1837 July 1. Concerning the Wilkes expedition (United States Exploring Expedition), use of India Rubber. 2 pages.
Paulding, James Kirke. Letter to Lieutenant Charles Wilkes. 1838 July 3. Encloses letters from Mr. N. L. Lee, who is soliciting appointment as carpenter. 1 page.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to Robert M. Patterson. 1838 November 13. Life aboard the Peacock on the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to to John K. Kane. 1840 April 5. Accounts of adventures with United States Exploring Expedition. Discovery of Antarctic Continent. 4 pages.
Jay, John C. Letter to Benjamin Tappan. 1843 February 8. Applies to work on shells brought back by Wilkes Expedition (United States Exploring Expedition). 2 pages.
Prime, Frederick. Letter to Joseph L. Tillinghast. 1843 February 11. Recommends Mr. Jay as conchologist to report on specimens returned to Wilkes. 2 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to George Ord. 1843 March 14. Complains of the manner in which members of the late Exploring Expedition (the United States Exploring Expedition) were treated upon return. 2 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to George Ord. 1844 November 26. Forwards newspaper containing Senator Tappan's Plan for the investment of the Smithsonian bequest. Related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 2 pages.
Ord, George. Letter to Titian R. Peale. 1844 December 4. Hopes the American Philosophical Society will receive a copy of Captain Wilkes' book. 3 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to George Ord. 1845 April 7. Introducing Mr. William Rich, botanist of the late United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
Ord, George. Letter to Titian R. Peale. 1845 May 20. Concerning identity of a partridge. Charles Wilkes has promised the American Philosophical Society a copy of his work. 2 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to George Ord. 1845 July 3. May present himself for appointment as superintendent of National Gallery if Captain Wilkes of the late United States Exploring Expedition resigns or is removed. 3 pages.
Ord, George. Letter to Titian R. Peale. 1845 December 21. Has "not read a page" of Wilkes' Narrative. 4 pages.
Dana, James Dwight. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1848 October 3. Is working on the geological report and the marine crustacea. 1 page.
Ord, George. Letter to Titian R. Peale. 1852 January 27. "I have been long persuaded there was a plot concocted to defraud you of the produce of your labors" in connection to the United States Exploring Expedition. 4 pages.
Ord, George. Letter to Titian R. Peale. 1852 December 4. Injustice of treatment accorded to Mr. Peale in connection with his work on the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
Wilkes, Charles. Letter to William Pitt Fessenden. 1857 February 20. Concerns the publication of the information collected during the United States Exploring Expedition of 1838-1842. 4 pages.
Tennessee Historical Society. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1857 September 2. Certificate of election to the Tennessee Historical Society. 1 page.
New York (N.Y.), Common Council. Letter to Captain Charles Wilkes, U.S.N. 1861 November 25. Granting the freedom of the city to Captain Charles Wilkes for his service in the capture of Mason and Slidell. 1 page.
New York (N.Y.), Common Council. Letter to Captain Charles Wilkes, U.S.N. 1861 November 25. Resolutions adopted upon the capture of Mason and Slidell. 2 pages.
O'Connell, Maurice, Sir. Letter to Captain Charles Wilkes. Tuesday morning. He and lady O'Connell accept invitation. 1 page.
Early American History Note
J. Stephen Catlett wrote of the Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection that “there is no other way to describe these manuscript letters, essays, and other papers that are contained presently in 49 boxes.” Catlett then listed a random assortment of names of authors found in the collection. Each individual item was catalogued in the card catalogue, but his data has now been put online. Rather than try to replicate that data, this entry will focus on some of the main themes of the collection and some of the most notable documents.
Among the many singular items are a letter by John Locke (in French); a letter by Isaac Newton; a receipt of Josiah Franklin's; letters by William Pitt; a letter from Patience Lovell Wright, a sculptor turned spy for the Americans during the Revolution (although the letter predates Independence, it does show her support for the colonies); and notes by and letters to Crevecoeur.
There is also a heretofore unpublished essay on the reasons for and a detail of the Albany plan of union.
The collection also contains interesting odds and ends, such as the story of John Kinsey’s death and the strange circumstances surrounding it in which he had a detailed premonition of his demise the night before. Also of note is a letter from one of Deborah Franklin’s cousins that relates the birth of Deborah's son in 1768.
The collection also has a heavy focus on Pennsylvania and Philadelphia history, especially in the early period. There are some early and official documents, such as an original William Penn grant to Thomas Powell. Some of these documents are potentially research-rich, such as the alphabetical listing of all grants of land in the colony from 1682-1698 and a list of the lots in Philadelphia granted from 1682-1692 that also has a partial sketch of Mulberry and Sassafras Streets. There is also what may be one of the first drafts of Philadelphia’s charter and the finished official charters of Philadelphia and Chester. There is a fair amount on colonial politics, especially in the correspondence of James Logan.
In addition, there are many wills, various bonds, some inventories and surveys, and legal documents on the care of orphans.
There is also an interesting series of Benjamin Rush’s letters written in 1768 that touch on affairs of the heart and make mention of Rush’s support for the colonies in their struggles with the “Mother Country.”
The Revolutionary era documents include letters from William Strahan to David Hall that supplement the APS’s Hall and Strahan collections. The letters often touch on political matters, including Strahan’s belief that nonimportation was an ineffective means of protest. A significant number of other items touch on Revolution-era activities and circumstances.
For the post-War period, there is a fascinating narrative of a rebellion in Lewistown, Pennsylvania in 1790 that involved a judge. There is also a notebook by Jonathan Donath on beekeeping that is identical to the other one in the APS collection, although this one appears to be the original and includes a reference to George Washington and others visiting Donath's apiary during the Constitutional Convention. This period also has a number of letters from Thomas FitzSimmons, a prominent Philadelphia politician and one of the only Catholic signers of the Constitution.
There is also a remarkable petition from female residents of Philadelphia requesting those held in Philadelphia jails because of Fries Rebellion be released.
For the nineteenth century, the collection shifts toward material about science and about the Philadelphia elite.
Included in the scientific material are notes, letters, notebooks, and meteorological diaries. There are also a series of records relating to the transportation revolution, including notes from Loammi Baldwin and canal engineering, and numerous letters regarding steam boats and internal improvements.
The Vaughan family have a heavy presence in the collection, though almost all material from John was in 2010 removed to a separate collection. Miscellaneous Manuscripts also has a series of Matthew Carey correspondence.
One of the more noteworthy themes of the collection is of people writing about history and historical memory. There is a fascinating translation of letters from an unnamed Frenchman who describes the histories of various colonies and the American Revolution from his perspective. There are records of Lafayette’s visit to US in 1824-1825. The collection also has an large number of notes from Moredcai Jacobs in which he adds his own memory of events and places depicted in John Watson’s Annals of Philadelphia. Finally, there are many letters from Jared Sparks seeking letters and documents on Benjamin Franklin.
Arctic Indians; Beyond Early America; Cayuga Indians; Colonial Politics; Early National Politics; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Gelatin silver prints; General Correspondence; History of science and technology.; Inuit--Canada; Iroquois Indians; Isleta Indians; Miscellaneous; Mohawk Indians; Natural History; Negatives; Ojibwa Indians; Oneida Indians; Onondaga Indians; Penobscot Indians; Photomechanical prints; Physics -- History.; Scientific Correspondence; Seneca Indians; Slides.; Southwest Indians; Tuscarora Indians; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783
- Papers
  - Agreement with John Prudden to keep a school in Roxborough, Feb. 25, 1668; 13x8; Eliot, John, 1604-1690
    Scope and Contents note
    Photo. (?) of D.S. by 7 persons. 1p.
  - Letter to Dr. [John] North, April 21, 1677; 7 1/4" x 11 3/4"; Newton, Isaac, Sir, 1642-1727
    Cambridge, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Presented by the Royal society of London, through Dr. Frank Aydelotte, Nov. 1945. See Nature, Aug 18,1945,p.193, for printed ed. of letter and an account of it.
  - Patent to Virginia, Oct. 10, [1677]; 7-1/2x12-1/2; Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685
    Westminster, D. 2p. Copy.
  - Account book, Dec., 1677., [1672]; 18x12-1/2
    D. 2p. Incomplete. Presented by C.H.Hill; June 15.
  - Letter to Sir John Moore, Aug. 29, 1678; 7-1/2x6; Banks, John
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Concerning the election of an M.P. from Hull. On same sheet is draft of a letter, pertaining to the same election.
  - Indenture for 500 acres of land in the county of Chester granted to Thomas Powell, March 22, 1681; 26" x 23"; Penn, William, 1644-1718
    D.S. 1p. and end. ca. Parchment.
  - Charter granted by Charles II to William Penn, March 4, 1682; 23 1/2" x 17 1/2"; Pennsylvania. Charters
    Photostat of D. Sec.1,2,4. From original in Archives of Pennsylvania. Facsimile in Pa. Archives, ser.2, v.7,pt.2. Printed: 345.12:P38h,81 and various other places.
  - Alphabetical listing of warrants for lots in Philadelphia, on the west side of the city towards the Schuylkill, but includes lots at the center of the city, 1682/3-1692; 12-1/2x8; Pennsylvania. Surveyor general's office
    D. 2p. Film 403 Frame 42
  - List of warrants and returns of surveys of lots, lands, etc. received of Silas Crispin, 1683-1694; 12x7-3/4; Pennsylvania. Surveyor general's office
    []. D. 2p. Film 403 Frame 41
  - Letter to [Otto Mencke, May 30, [1693 ?]; 11 3/4" x 7 1/4"; Newton, Isaac, Sir, 1642-1727
    A.Dr. of L. 1p. Pertains to copies of the Acta eruditorum sent in exchange for his [Principia]. With this is a photostat of printed description and translation of the letter by S.A. Ives. Printed:Turnbull, Corres., III, 270. MICROFILM FRAME NO.737
  - Letter to Sir John Moore, Feb. 27, 1695/6; 6x5-3/4; Banks, John
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Recommends a family for charity.
  - An account of certain books, Oct. 27, 1698; 12x7-3/4; Pennsylvania. Surveyor general's office
    []. writings, etc. belonging to the Surveyor-General's Office, received from Thomas Jenner by Edward Penington; D. 40p. Film 403 Frame 40
  - Account of lots returned [Front, High, Walnut, Chestnut, Mulberry, 2nd Streets: 2nd and 4th Streets: etc.], Oct. 27, 1698; 12-1/2x8; Pennsylvania. Surveyor general's office
    D. 11p. Film 403 Frame 40
  - Alphabetical listing of surveys,from Assistant Surveyors, in New Castle, Sussex and Kent Counties, and loss in Philadelphia, June 19, 1700; 12x7-3/4; Pennsylvania. Surveyor general's office
    (?), D. 6p. Film 403 Frame 41
  - Will, Sept. 7, 1700; 13x8; Vaughan, John
    Philadelphia, D.S.by mark of John Vaughan. 1p. Witnessed: Sam. Richardson, Dav. Lloyd, and Elizabeth Phelps. Seal. Mutilated. (This John Vaughan was a Philadelphia carpenter).
  - Marriage bond - John Read and Sarah White, Feb. (?) 23, 1701; Read, John
    Photostat of printed D. filled in in ms. 1p. and end. From original in the Diocesan Registry, Lichfield, England. These are the parents of Deborah Read Franklin. FILM54-Family FRAME 1
  - Charter granted by William Penn, Oct. 25, 1701; 12" x 7 1/2"; Philadelphia. Charters
    Philadelphia, Copy of D. 11p. Contemporary copy; probably the one sent to William Penn with proposed charter of 1706 - cf. Wolf, E. The 1706 charter of Philadelphia, APS Library Bulletin,1952,pp.388-405.
    - Pennsylvania Charter of Privileges, 1701; 1.0 Item(s); William Penn's Charter of Privileges, creating a frame for Pennsylvania government.
  - Deed for tract of land at Front and High Streets, Philadelphia, to John Smart, Oct. 27, 1701; 12" x 15"; Penn, Letitia
    Ms.D.S. 1p. and end. Seals
  - Charter of privileges to the province of Pennsylvania...Philadelphia, Oct. 28, 1701; 26 1/4" x 30 1/2", 25" x 29 1/2"; Penn, William, 1644-1718
    D.S. 2p. parchment seal. Acknowledgment signed: Jos. Growdon, speaker; Edwd. Shippen, Phineas Pemberton, Sam. Carpenter, Griffith Owen, Caleb Pusey, Tho. Story, propry and governrs council. Recorded...31st 8th mo. 1701 - signed: Tho. Story. Printed: Colonial records, v.2,pp.56-60. FEB.7,1812 Presented by Joseph Anthony; cf. Minutes, Jan. 17,1812. ---- ---- photographs (full size, and 8" x 10").
  - [The charter to privileges granted by William Penn, to the inhabitants of Pensilvania and territories], October 28, 1701; 29" x 25"; Pennsylvania. Charters
    D.S: Wm. Penn [and others] 2 pieces of parchment, approx. Seal. This is the original charter; it was presented by Joseph Anthony, cf. Minutes Jan. 17 and Feb. 7, 1812. Charters of the province of Pensilvania...Philadelphia, Franklin,1742,p.17. Also in Colonial records, v.2, 1852,p.56. Framed, hangs in Green room of the Hall of the Society. ---- Portion of copy of the Charter. 2p.
  - Charter of the borough of Chester, October 31, 1701; 31 1/2" x 25 1/2" and 31 1/2" x 15"; Penn, William, 1644-1718
    Parchment D.S.: Wm. Penn. 2 sheets, Seal. End: Recorded in the Rolls Office at Philadelphia in Patent book A - Vol.2,page 138 to 141 - this 6th 9br 1701 By me Tho. Story... Printed: Hazard's Register of Pennsylvania,v.3,p. 264
  - Bill to the town of Boston for candles delivered to the alms house, Feb.26, Oct. 27, 1703; 4" x 7"; Franklin, Josiah, 1658-1745
    allowed Nov. 8 (?), 1703. A.D.S. 1p. and end. FILM54-63 FRAME 47
  - Proposed charter, 1706; 32"x32", 32"x 23"; Philadelphia. Charters
    D. 2p. - Parchment. See Wolf, E. The 1706 charter of the city of Philadelphia, in Library Bulletin for 1952. pp.388-405.
    Not Found: 2/10/2011
  - [Ordinance for establishing courts of judicature;], February 22, 1706; 23 1/2" x 30"; Pennsylvania. Lieutenant Governor (1704-1709: Evans)
    Parchment D.S: John Evans. 1p. Seal. End: Recorded in the Rolls Office at Philada in Patent Book A vol. 4 p the 16th 2d mo 1707. By me Tho. Story... Printed: Statutes at large of Pennsylvania, 1682-1801, v.2,1896,p.500.
  - Receipt to Mdm. Shrimpton, Feb. 14, 1707/8; 4 1/2" x 2 1/2"; Franklin, Josiah, 1658-1745
    A.D.S. 1p. FILM54-family FRAME 2
  - Order to Jacob Taylor to survey a certain tract of land for John Gumly, May 7, 1712; 7 1/2" x 12 1/4"; Pennsylvania. Commissioners of Property
    Phila., D.S: Edwd. Shippen, Richard Hill, Isaac Norris, James Logan 1p.and end. Seal. FILM 403 FRAME 45
  - Letter to the Governor [William Penn], Feb. 26, 1712/13; 12 1/2" x 8"; Logan, James, 1674-1751
    Phila., 26th 12mo 1712/13 A.L.S. 4p. Management of government of Pennsylvania established of the Pennsylvania-Mary-land boundary. Printed: Pa. archives, s.2,v.7,31.
  - Commission to William Keith to be Lieutenant Governor of the province of Pennsylvania and counties of Newcastle, Kent and Sussex on Delaware, Nov. 29, 1716; 7 1/2" x 12"; Penn, William, 1644-1718
    Copy of D. 4p., end. Contains also note S: R. Peters.
  - Letter to Abraham Gronovius, Oxford, Sept., 1717; 10x8; Gronovius, Johannes Fredericus, 1686-1762
    Photo.of A.L.S. 1p.and add. In Dutch. (from original in Universität Bibliothek, University of Munich.)
  - Letter to Abraham [Gronovius], Jan. 30, 1717; 10x8; Gronovius, Johannes Fredericus, 1686-1762
    Photo.of A.L.S. 2p.and end. In Dutch. (from original in Universität Bibliothek, University of M,,nich.)
  - Letter to Abraham Gronovius, London, Dec. 16, 1717; 10x8; Gronovius, Johannes Fredericus, 1686-1762